I apologize for the lack of YouTube
videos recently I'm still a little bit
burnt out but I'm doing my
[Music]
best okay let's go we played him twice
actually
so I'm not going to play repeat
opponents too many times unless there's
nobody else to play oh my God chess
Meister 2
2431 that's a pretty darn High rating
well let's go 2431 let's go Knight F6
and obviously against the player this
high rated this is the highest rated
player we've faced in the speedrun ever
so I have to play my main repertoire
that I can't dier around here which
means we're going to play the Kings
Indian and our opponent is trotting out
the fian ketto variation which is one of
the most reputable and positionally
dangerous responses is against the
king's Indian of course it's the line
where white plays G3 and Fen ketto is
their kingside bishop and then typically
Castle's kingside now so far we have not
committed to a king's Indian we commit
to a king's Indian when we push the D
Pawn up to D6 we can also play this in a
grunfeld fashion we can castle and push
D5 or we can play this in a grunfeld
slav fashion and this is the
recommendation of a lot of sort of
modern day chess literature which is to
play C 6 and then D5 and that line does
equalize there's no doubt about that but
it's more fun and more in the spirit of
my repertoire to play this in a more
traditional Kings Indian fashion which
is why we play D6 and here we reach a
very wide theoretical Crossroads black
has a million different setups against
the fian ketto variation and I would say
that these setups are broadly divided
into three categories there are setups
where black prepares E5 this is what
we're going to play in this game because
this is the most traditional and Kings
Indian esque variation there are setups
that involve playing the move C5 this is
what GNE Jones recommends in his
chessable course This lends the flavor a
more Bon uh lends the game a more Bon
flavor then there are systems where you
play neither E5 nor C5 at least not
immediately you can play C6 um you can
play Bishop F5 you can play Knight C6
and A6 which is the Pano variation one
of the main lines against thean ketto so
there's a anging number of variations
and they're all pretty decent but we're
going to choose the one that I've played
for the longest time and that's Knight B
to D7 and quickly pushing E5 now White's
main response is to strike back in the
center with E4 and that's what our
opponent plays and here I've played two
different variations in my chess career
the first is he takes D4 at trading off
in the center immediately then paying a
visit to C5 with the Knight and putting
pressure on this you could think of it
as a moroi bind this is not a maroi bind
refers specifically to the structure
that occurs in the accelerated Dragon um
but you can think of the pawns on e4 and
C4 as kind of a moroi bind like
construction and this position does
resemble an accelerated dragon in that
after e takes D4 black is cramped and
white is a big space Advantage but black
applies longlasting pressure to White
Center and if white doesn't handle the
position with great care then White
Center can collapse but in this game I'd
like to play a second line and this is
an older Line This is what I used to
play over the board when I was you know
up until International Master Level and
I still play this almost exclusively in
Blitz because it's an incredibly tricky
line and it's a line that often slips
through the cracks of even very
experienced uh fian ketto players so you
start with the move C6 and again if
you've watched my stream then you've
probably seen me play this line the
point of the line is to bring the queen
out to A5 I might have even had this in
a speedrun game at some point so you
know if if memory serves me right but
this line is incredibly tricky and our
opponent already demonstrates very very
good knowledge of this system the move
Bishop E3 is the sort of new
recommendation um as far as I know this
is what like the top Grand Masters play
nowadays the old move which almost
everybody played up until a year ago was
rookie one and I'll give you the lowdown
on this line after the game I'll give
you some theoretical overview and I'll
show some cool traps after Bishop E3
we're supposed to release the tension
with e takes D4 this is Theory so I'm
not explaining these moves uh deeply I'm
just making them because they're the
theoretical moves at this point we
discharge the tension in the center and
the reason we do it I think at at this
precise moment is because white is
already prepared to push D5 and close
the center down and the bishop on E3 is
very harmoniously played so this is sort
of last opportunity to exchange the
pawns before white closes the center and
white is at a further Crossroads there's
Bishop takes D4 and there's the more
traditional recapture which is of course
Knight takes D4 most of the time when
black plays Ed White doesn't even have
the option of Bishop takes D4 so most
players who are not as experienced kind
of automatically play Knight takes D4
clearly our opponent realized that
there's a choice to be made here and
make no mistake like if you run this
through the computer yeah white is
better what white has to demonstrate
tremendous precision as is true in most
Kings Indian lines in order to prove
that advantage and from the point of
view of a rapid game black has a lot of
easy moves black has a lot of ways to
create threats and if black seizes the
initiative you know what happens in a
Kings Indian where black has the
initiative so I really really believe in
this line and hopefully I'll be able to
demonstrate it against a really really
strong player our opponent is thinking
I'm pretty sure you had this in a
previous speedrun game since soup the
Sailor I'm pretty sure of that too maybe
even in this speedrun although I don't
remember when I feel like I have
definitely played this queen A5
variation um before so if if you
remember that game you can let me know
but doesn't really matter um it's been I
think a sufficient amount of time has
passed so our opponent plays The
Annoying move I didn't want to say what
the what the annoying move was just in
case but Bishop takes D4 is the move I
really dislike playing against the
reason is that your standard response
will be knight5 but in response to
knight5 White has a tactic and this
tactic just kills the line knight5 is
almost a decisive mistake Believe It or
Not does anybody know what the idea is
against Knight E5 and that is why we
have to keep this Knight on D7 for the
time being if we play Knight E5 we walk
into what do we walk into it's a very
unusual tactical idea very unusual
extremely yes C
white undermines the Knight with C5 and
typically you just able to take on F3
but white recaptures with the queen and
the Knight on F6 is suddenly hanging
right that's the power of recapturing
with the bishop so Knight E5 walks into
C5 and that is why we want to make a
more flexible move so let's make let's
sort of pick the lwh hanging fruit and
start with Rook E8 which is a move that
will not harm our position that is for
sure let's wait for white to kind of
show his cards and then then we'll make
a more substantive decision about how to
position our pieces it'll it's possible
that our Queen on A5 has done its job
and should drop back to C7 in order to
make Knight E5 possible because we can't
keep this Knight on D7 forever it blocks
the bishop on C8 and it causes our
position to be very cramped we of course
can deploy the Knight to C5 but I like
that a lot less in this position for a
couple of reasons one of which is that
with the queen on A5 and the Knight on
C5 obviously white has like a34 ideas
but also Knight C5 just seems very
flimsy maybe white can push in the
center with E5 and white can very easily
defend the E4 Pawn so while Knight C5
might be tempting to attack the E4 Pawn
I really really think that the Knight is
better positioned on E5 in this line and
these are the sorts of things that you
just feel right when you play a line
many times you make a lot of mistakes
and at some point you start developing a
finer understanding of where the pieces
belong and it can't always be explained
verbally like step by step like this is
exactly why this piece goes here and
that that piece goes there a lot of it
has to do with feel okay so Rook E1 and
I do think we should drop our Queen back
to C7 because Knight E5 still allows
C5 um and the Queen on A5 is kind of
neither here nor there so I'm I'm very
much inclined to play Queen C7 and then
jump out to E5 with our Knight we've got
other ways that we can maneuver around
the you know the hurdles we can play
Knight f8 and Knight E6 kind of a Ru
Lopez style idea but this to me seems a
lot more King's Indian esque in nature
let's go Knight let's go queen queen C7
yeah cramped position for sure cramped
position but a very solid position
classic Kings Indian
situation what was the idea a lot of
people are asking what was the idea of
Queen A5 I will explain that after the
game it's it's harder to see it because
of what our opponent played which is
Bishop E3 if our opponent had played the
main move which is rookie1 then I think
you would have really understood the
value of this queen sometimes it can
swing over to H5 that's like one easy
thing to to understand and the other
like broad thing is that it aims at the
Knight on C3 so the move B3 is a very
useful move for white in these positions
to defend the C4 Pawn with the queen on
A5 B3 is not possible and it's actually
a very common Blender at lower levels
I've even beaten title players like this
they play B3 automatically without
realizing that the Knight is now hanging
so in many situations when the C4 Pawn
is attacked from B6 or E5 it's actually
very hard to defend that pawn adequately
if you've got if you don't have the
ability to play B3 okay Queen C2 well
our opponent continues to improve his
position I think that we should do the
same and we should probably follow
through on our plan and play Knight E5 I
think black has a pretty decent position
here I think white has a very powerful
move here super Advanced move we'll see
if our opponent finds it this is a very
Advanced move I think most people who
look at this position like most people
would take on E5 but generally that
trade favors black and the reason is
really simple I've talked about this at
length before when you get the quote
unquote symmetrical Pawn structure in
the Kings Indian it's actually not
symmetrical at all and the chief
difference is that White's got pawns on
C4 and E4 so white is a big big weakness
on the D4 Square which really comes out
in the event the black plays D takes C5
black on the other hand has this Pawn on
C6 which is restricting the Knight on C3
so Knight takes C5 is a positional
mistake here in my opinion and I've won
a lot of games in that structure because
ultimately you just shuttle your knight
around to D4 and our of course plays the
advanced move I had no doubt in my mind
and now we reach a I think a very
important position so Knight D2 drops
the Knight away and protects C4 clearly
it's also preparing the move F4 now F4
is not the end of the world it sends our
Knight back to D7 but in the king's
Indian you have to be totally
comfortable moving pieces back and forth
with that said I don't want to allow F4
because I really really do I want to try
to entrench and establish this Knight on
E5 if at all possible so we ask
ourselves the question is it possible to
stop F4 and I actually think it is we
can make a position Al risky move this
is a risky move it's it has its
drawbacks but this is what the kinian is
all about you have to know and feel the
situations in which such moves are
necessary what what are we talking about
here this move does not physically
prevent F4 but it discourages it I'm
talking about the move G5 this in and of
itself is a construction that you might
find familiar like you put a knight on
E5 and then you put a pawn two squares
away you do this if you translate this
to the right side of the board in the
king's Indian you play Knight C5 and
then A5 it's the same exact principle if
white plays F4 now my idea is to trade
once on F4 and drop the Knight back to
G6 to put more pressure on the F4 Pawn
then the situation gets a lot more
tactical which is really to my liking I
feel like our King is a little bit safer
than whites in that position thank you
red
Calamity all right so we're trying to
also the move G5 has opened up the G
Square for the Knight so Knight G6 is
only a move made possible by the push of
the pawn why am I not more worried about
the weakness that we create first of all
this is less drastic of a weakening move
than it may appear because you know we
still have our fien ketto Bishop our
King is still safe it's not like we play
G5 and the world ends yes it's a risky
move positionally also because we weaken
the F5 Square so often times you will
see white immediately burying the Knight
over to E3 but the F5 square is also
guarded by our light squ Bishop so I'm
not too worried about an outpost on F5
in the near future it's kind of hard for
white to find a move here this is what I
find to be the case in the fian ketto
variation white just burns a ton of time
black is worse objectively cramped yes
but sometimes Black's play is just more
clearly defined okay so our opponent has
spent close to half their time and it's
only move 14 I'm already keeping a close
eye on White's clock what's our next
move going to be well we've got a couple
of you know again I call this lwh
hanging fruit by which I refer to moves
that you you know that these moves are
not going to hurt your position so what
are like the easy things that we can do
well first of all we can develop this
bishop but we need to be mindful of
where we develop it I think most people
would be tempted by Bishop B6 but after
Bishop B6 white can play B3 and that's
not the issue the issue is that
subsequently when white plays the move
F4 we're in trouble because we cannot
play Knight G6 white pushes F5 forking
our Bishop in our Knight so actually it
might be a better idea to play the more
modest move Bishop to D7 right so that
F4 could still be met after the
preliminary exchange with the move
Knight G6 what other moves can we
consider well we actually can play H5
and try to go G4 this is a more advanced
and involved plan because it weakens
more of our King side but if we can play
the moves H5 and G4 what we do is create
a essentially lifetime bind on the king
side because then anytime that white
will try to play F4 we will take on pant
and weaken White's King side
tremendously so that's a more you know
plan that is involved with more risk in
terms of small improving moves other
than Bishop D7 I don't see all that much
that we can do B B3 okay so B3 gives us
a pretty wide Choice our opponent just
kind of passing the move I really like
the plan of H5 and G4 and you might ask
C can we play G4 immediately the answer
is no because then white plays H takes
G4 and the whole purpose of that move is
defeated we're not actually stopping
white from playing F4 so really I think
the choice is between Bishop D7 and H5
and as a self-respecting Kings Indian
player I almost always air on the side
of the more you know the rier the more
interesting move the move that's more
challenging and I think H5 is a very
challenging move especially in light of
White's clock situation because our
opponent will now see that we want to go
G4 what does that mean well that means
he's going to start calculating F4
because F4 is a serious candidate move
and this might be White's last chance to
play that move because after we play G4
we will get that bind in place I like H5
I think it's a I think it's a very
testing move okay less than S minutes
now now for our opponent not to get to
trans fixed on the clock but it is a
very important factor uh in any position
and now that we've reached this higher
level in the speedrun you know I'm I'm
telling you exactly the sorts of things
that I would focus on in a real rapid
game and in a real rapid game I would
already be like pretty much obsessed
with White's clock and making moves that
are simultaneously healthy but also give
white a big Choice okay I I hate it when
people pretend that you know you're not
supposed to talk about the clock because
it's not a legitimate part of the game
it absolutely is and knowing how to
handle both your and your opponent's
clock will give you massive massive
rating
bonuses okay we're waiting for our
opponent's response here obviously he's
going to start playing a lot faster in
just a couple moves here I would I would
imagine yeah
so Rook a D1 yeah this is what I thought
white would do our opponent is just sort
of making St forward improving moves
let's just make sure that G4 is the best
that we can do of course we can also
play the move H4 and the move H4 is a
very sensible candidate move actually it
might be worth spending a little bit
more time contemplating this move than
it may appear what's so great about the
move H4 well H4 is a classic positional
idea you are trying to lure white into
playing G4 and if white plays G4 then
again the move F4 is virtually
impossible to achieve we get get this
big big bind on the dark squares in the
center so H4 very much possible white
can take and play F4 but that leads us
to once again serious complications on
the king side that I think might favor
black but I'm not sure I mean that that
is a very complicated position so we can
go G4 as originally planned we can do
neither we can play Bishop D7 here and
kick the can down the road right since
we're not too worried about white
playing
F4 this is a hard hard a hard decision
but my inclination is to play G4 my
heavy inclination is to play G4 but the
move G4 is also associated with
positional risk because it weakens for
example the F4 Square so one thing that
white could do is shutter shuttle this
KN around to F4 not that that's such a
big huge cataclysmic square but still we
should be mindful of the squares that
we're weakening when we push our pawns
like this okay let's go G4 this just I
feel like this has to be the move this
is this is principled
it's what we've been building up toward
and it would be a big relief if we
didn't constantly have to worry about
the prospect of
f4 okay HG well obviously we play HG
white buys himself a Tempo but I would
draw your attention to the fact that the
H file is now open and we're not as far
away as it may appear from exploiting
that I think we're actually like three
or four moves away from being able to
pick up on that H file we can play
something like Bishop H6 King G7 and
Rook h8 bang now when a rook gets to h8
it's not Checkmate but at least we
create the potential preconditions for
tactics on the H file we can even
consider King h8 King H7 King G6 and
Rook h8 but I would rule that out on the
basis of this Knight maneuver to F4
which will send our King right back to
H7 and so that's why it's so important
to constantly keep in your mind a list
of the squares that you're weakening
when you when you play a lot with your
pawns because that helps you rule out C
options like okay I know that F4 is a
weakness so I need to be mindful of this
maneuver I know that F5 is weak is a
weakness I need to be mindful of this
maneuver there we go knight2 okay now
things are getting spicy our opponent
walking around to F4 let's let's think
for a second so I guess one question is
do we want to prevent or try to
discourage Knight F4 or do we not care
if we don't care then we can play Bishop
H6 and keep going with our plan if we do
care one thing we can consider is the
move Knight to H5 and I actually really
like the look of Knight H5 because it's
not easy to see how Knight H5 actually
stops Knight F4 and it doesn't white can
still play Knight F4 but after Knight
takes F4 G takes F4 Knight G6 we trade
the Bishops and White's got this
long-lasting weakness on F4 that's
actually going to be I think really hard
to defend the position there gets super
spicy but maybe it's a little bit on the
dubious side
okay I'm going to think some more ah
I've come up with another interesting
idea I've come up with another very
interesting idea this one is really cute
what if we go not Knight H5 but Knight
to H7 what if we try Knight H7 here I'm
looking at this F3 square and I really
would like to increase our bind over
these light squares that we have
garnered by pushing the pawn of G4 and
it makes sense I think to bring this
Knight around to G5 so that it can jump
into F3 jump into H3 and in general just
crab legs on the king
side it's got its drawbacks like the
Knight on G5 is not stable it can be
pretty easily attacked for instance with
White's Bishop but I think in light of
White's clock situation we should give
this move a shot Knight
H7 the best move in
chess okay Bishop B3 preventing Knight
G5 but I saw that and I thought we could
reinforce that with Queen E7 or Bishop
Bishop
F6 let's think about this for a little
while longer because now white actually
might be preparing Knight to D4 followed
by Knight F5 we should keep track of
that idea as we devise our next
move okay so the the the options here
are to play Bishop F6 Queen E7
everything to prepare Knight G5 okay I
need to think in silence for a bit here
this is an important position Rook E6 is
also interesting by the way o like h i
could spend 30 minutes on this position
which I'm not going to do don't
worry okay I'm going to go with my
initial idea we're going to go Queen E7
here we're going to go Queen E7 and this
is I think the most obvious move right
you're bringing the queen from C7 to E7
where it is a little bit more equipped
to join the action on the king side but
the main idea is to prepare Knight G5
now you might look at say well I don't
understand why Knight G5 is even on our
plate here because can play Bishop takes
G5 but the trade of the bishop for the
Knight gives us a monopoly over the dark
squares right then our Bishop on G7 is
going to be really happy now this is
what I was worried about this is an
incredible maneuver by White Knight E2
Bishop E3 and Knight C4 way over my head
to be honest but okay we're going to
deal with that we're going to deal with
it by trying to adopt an interesting
defensive setup here's what I was
thinking we might do here's what I was
thinking we might do I think that we
should go
I think we should go Queen F6 here just
getting the queen onto its optimal
Square getting the queen to its optimal
Square I'm expecting white to play
Knight F5 here right and complete his
maneuver and after Knight F5 we should
resist with every fiber of our being the
temptation to play Bishop takes F5 I
think that would be a serious positional
mistake because following e takes F5 not
only have we given up a light squir
bishop and our whole play on the king
side is predicated on light squ control
so we need this bishop for future use
but in addition more importantly after
Knight F5 Bishop F5 EF white gets this
juicy E4 Square for his other Knight
then the D6 Pawn will collapse and then
our whole position collapses so it's so
important this Pawn on e4 is what's
saving our life because all of White's
pieces want that square for themselves
so after Knight F5 we're going to drop
our Bishop back to f8 in order to lend
an additional Defender to this D6 pawn
and I know looks really
awkward but I actually think it's a very
watertight defensive construction Rook
F1 is not scary unless our opponent is
preparing
F4 which I kind of assumed was not
achievable but I guess it
is so we can play Knight G5 we can also
try to throw in Bishop H6 and trade the
dark squ Bishops which as I discussed
was a good idea positionally but maybe
bishop H6 fails tactically I don't
know again need to think in silence for
a bit because this gets super
complicated I like the look of Bishop H6
from a positional standpoint but it's
also risky because you give up the
king's Indian Bishop which is also a
defensive Maverick in such
positions really really hard decisions
here that our opponent is making us take
yeah I I honestly don't know whether we
should play Bishop H6 or not my
positional sense is telling me yes but
tactically I'd be really scared of our
King safety I think the X Factor here
might be White's clock I'm going to make
a bet that white does not have enough
time to punish us for the move Bishop
H6 well of course the guyy is 2400 he's
he's probably like strong Master Level
IRL so this is with black it's not going
to be an easy game I'm not wasn't
expecting one I was not expecting an
easy game I think both of our sets of
pieces are very nicely placed this has
been a highle maneuvering game I'm proud
of the way that that I played on the
king side and we are just looking a
couple steps away from really
instituting a an an Unstoppable bind on
the king side yes white still looks very
solid but here's what could happen let's
say white trades on H6 we're able then
to get our Knight to G5 at that point we
will be only two moves away from setting
up Unstoppable threats remember that old
friend King G7 and Rook h8 well that's
kind of what I'm aiming toward C5 Jesus
that I was absolutely not even close to
being on my radar like I saw this
possibility but I didn't think he would
play it here guess it's a good move I
don't know and if we take take and go
Queen H6 here at that point the pawn
structure gets really bad for white so
that is very attractive to me very
attractive yeah we're not resisting oh
but Knight C4 ah but Knight takes C4 my
gosh it gets complicated let's take and
queen H6 why Queen H6 and not Queen G5
because we want to reserve the G5 Square
for our Knight are am I sure that we're
going to go Knight G5 of course not the
position is highly unpredictable but you
have to set yourself up for Success now
we've created concrete weaknesses in
White's position that are easy to attack
the drawback of course is that we've
given white the f file why don't I care
about that because I feel like there's
nothing on the f file for white now
we're looking for some tactics I'm
looking at the Rook I'm also looking at
this D3 Square I think we can play DC
well we definitely should play DC anyway
regardless of what we're doing next and
after Queen C5 we have a forvic on D3
and sudden only White's position showing
some signs of weakness what's funny is
we might actually refrain from playing
Knight D3 because there's a case to be
made that this Knight on E5 is such a
strong piece that it's not worth winning
the exchange for it so after Queen takes
C5 it's it's probably worth considering
the move Knight to G5 so strong as our
Knight but probably we will in fact play
Knight D3 I I don't think I can resist
the temptation to win The Exchange okay
our opponent does not take on C5 seeing
Knight D3 okay so what happens now well
our Queen is hanging and as I mentioned
earlier Bishop takes F5 comes with a
very steep price tag after e takes F5
white gets the E4 Square for their
Knight but at this point the
circumstances have changed our Queen is
no longer on F6 so the move Knight E4 is
no longer going to come with Tempo so
how do we set ourselves up for the
possibility of Knight E4 well I
definitely think we should take this
Knight I don't think that we should let
this Knight exist on F5 and now I think
we should go Knight G5 I think this is
the critical move and largely Knight G5
is a prophylactic move actually o Knight
F6 would have been nice oh man I
completely forgot about that Knight F6
would have been awesome I forgot about
Knight F6 Knight G5 is a stubborn move
right this is what I always always
wanted to play so I still think it's a
good move because we have the prospect
now of playing Knight H3 check forcing
the exchange of Bishop for Knight and
the G3 Pawn is going to be super weak
and the other Knight is threatening to
jump into F3 suddenly White's position I
think is starting to crumble and it can
crumble really really fast because we're
not even done we can bring our Rook over
to d8 and intensify the pressure down
the center Knight C4 it feels like our
opponent is crumbling but we have to be
Uber precise in our execution here
and what that involves is deciding which
Knight we want to put on
F3 I think it should be Knight E to F3
but I'm not sure Knight E to F3 King F2
Knight
H3 yes I'm pretty sure that we should
play Knight ef3 here oh wait yeah okay
that that's kind of this is all
predicated on one very like flimsy line
that I just calculated and maybe I
should have spent longer but I'm pretty
sure that black is winning or maybe not
maybe not it's going to get super
tactical here which is why I'm really
happy we left ourselves with a lot of
time okay so here critical moment I
think a lot of you are tempted by the
move Queen H2 that's a terrible move for
many reasons but one of which is Rook
takes G4 and suddenly the Knight on G5
is pinned so we have an opportunity
train that we need to jump on right now
because we will not get another chance
to play this move and the move I'm
talking about is Knight H3 check
we stick that Knight in there before
it's too late forcing white to take it
otherwise we capture The Rook then we
take back with the queen and I didn't
see a defense for white in that position
I think we're just winning on the spot
here we're threatening to win White's
Queen with Queen H2 you should see that
that's a skewer but Queen H2 is a
standalone threat even if it didn't win
White's Queen it would lead to a mating
attack I pretty sure that white has no
defense here but maybe he'll find
something with his last seconds Rook
takes F3 by the way we still go Queen H2
we don't actually recapture The Rook
which is problematic for white because I
don't think white is a move man if we
can finish this one off that this would
be a really nice game I would be proud
of this one if if we're able to drive
this one home because this just shows
you how versatile and Rich of an opening
the Kings Indian is and in how many
different ways you can win a game in the
Kings Indian but let's count the
chickens when they've hatched no our
opponent actually played a very very
good game I think the mistakes came at
the very but wait all of this is a mood
Point Let's actually win but the win
here plays itself what we need to do is
drive the white king out into the center
and then deliver a decisive check with a
rook on d8 this is done with a zigzag
mechanism that you should be familiar
with you check on H2 you check on G1 you
staircase the queen to G2 the king is
driven out to the Target Square where it
is picked off by The Rook notice that
white has no threats down this diagonal
so we have nothing to worry about we
just deliver the checks and it's a moot
point any anyway because white isn't
able to Garner a Tempo Rook a d8 all
pieces are participating in the attack
in what is likely to be the final
position of the game unless our opponent
gives us the chance to deliver
mate and
resigns nice game okay our highest rated
opponent in the speedrun there's a lot
to talk about I won't bore you to death
with the opening Theory but definitely a
lot of context to to formulate I'm going
to pull up chest Bas just so I can um
make sure I'm not lying to when it comes
to Theory yeah super fun game and a lot
to explore I'm sure a lot of mistakes
were made by both of us it's impossible
not to in games this complex so we're
going to skip directly to the critical
position I won't you know explore the
theory of the other lines here if you
look at GNE Jones's chessable course you
can explore C5 here which I think is
maybe objectively the best move at some
point Knight C6 and A6 was all the rage
um as it was also against the sameish
but not as much anymore night D7 got
more popular uh in the last couple of
years at some point this fell out of
favor entirely so White Castles black
plays E5 of course E4 is not White's
only move the other main alternative is
Queen C2 and here you're supposed to
play E4 and Knight B6 very tricky line
that you've probably seen me playing
extensively in Blitz um but there's
definitely enough to enough to talk
about in the in the E4 line so again the
other line that I've played is e takes
D4 and Knight C5 which which does get a
very classic Pawn structure and i' I've
experienced this Pawn structure from the
black side for the majority of my chess
career I feel like I know the ins and
outs of the structure and all of the
Maneuvers and what makes it so
interesting is that the engine is always
skeptical in this structure about
Black's chances it's always 6 or8 and
that dissuades a lot of people from
going into it but you can trust me that
White's position is exceedingly hard to
play properly because there are so many
tricks there's just so many everything
here and Black's pieces have so much
potential that I truly believe that from
a practical standpoint you know this
structure is very much worthwhile for
for for black I have won countless quick
games in this structure with uh just an
endless amount of Tricks here's just one
quick example completely different
opening but you'll see the parallel so
this is a game that I played against a
very decent player like
1860 and this was not San Francisco this
was Reno I don't know why okay this is
ticking me off let
me Reno okay so here's what happens um
he plays an English and we reach this
structure right I play the king's Indian
it's a fiano English at first I played
the Knight C6 A6 plan and we reach this
structure right not exactly the same
thing but but it's defined by the pawns
on e4 and C4 Now watch how quickly his
position collapses Knight D7 and Knight
C5 typical Knight B4 and already he
makes the losing move here Knight D4 who
can tell me why this is a losing move
he's trying to contest the square on C6
completely forgetting why I put the
knights on B4 and C5 yeah this is a
chess base the the new theme because I
said it was very good nicely done what
does black do here Knight D3 which
Knight well not the one that's guarding
C6 this would walk into a fork rather
you play Knight CD3 interfering between
the queen and the Knight and attacking
The Rook but white goes Knight C6
deflecting in turn my knight but after
the trade I take this very important
Pawn on B2 and White's position
collapses then I went back to B4 took
another Pawn got my Bishop out and then
brought my queen over to B2 and he
resigned so I can show you a million
games like that where White Center
collapses really quickly and this isn't
even a line that happened in the game so
let's get to the actual matter at hand
which is the move C6 the older move so
white plays H3 which is standard fair in
this line the idea is to prepare Bishop
B3 and take away the G4 Square uh from
Black's Knight and you know potentially
even from the light squared Bishop still
Mainline Theory H3 and now the move
Queen A5 so as I explained earlier there
are broad level points to this move and
then there are like the specifics the
queen on A5 is a very powerful piece
because it's attacking from the side it
has the prospect of driving over to H5
which does happen in a line that I'm
about to show you and sometimes it can
even move into B4 which is a
surprisingly problematic move for white
to face so let's explore some lines and
hopefully these lines will not only
contextualize this line but kind of
start to give you an understanding of
why I really like this line and how
tricky it is white again has a way to
get an advantage several ways actually
but this requires not only vast
theoretical knowledge but knowledge of
all of Black's tricks and all of White's
key ideas let's examine some lines the
main move here is to play Rook E1 this
is the main
move and my computer's going to be a
little loud here just warning you in
response to Rook E1 you play e takes D4
Knight takes D4 and Knight E5 and here
here you see idea number one the
fundamental purpose of putting the queen
on A5 white cannot play B3 because he
drops C3 and it's hard to defend the C4
Pawn if white tries to do it with his
Queen okay if white tries to play Queen
E2 who can tell me actually not who can
tell me well who can tell me a way to
Fork the Knight on D4 and the pawn on C4
who can see the move bang bang Queen C5
there is another reason you put the
queen on A5 and in order not to be worse
white has to play a bunch of engine
moves like if Bishop E3 then you already
win the pawn and black has a great
position White's supposed to go Rook D1
which is a kind of a hard move to come
up with and here the position gets very
wild you play Knight takes C4 and
amazingly white is unable to separate
the queen from the Knight like white can
try Knight B3 but after Queen B4 Rook D4
um the Knight can be effectively
defended with either Bishop E6 or even
B5 and black is already better at this
point so this is one easy way to lose
the pawn for that reason most people
traditionally go Bishop F1 here this is
the main line of course this takes the
sting out of the move Queen C5 because
that no long well technically Queen C5
does hit the Knight that's funny but
here white has the move Knight B3 and
you can't take the pawn so Queen C5 is
futile for that reason you improve your
position with Rook to E
in the main line white completes his
development with Bishop B3 and so do we
and I've already shown this line in a
previous speedrun game in this position
tons of people walk into a beautiful
tactic I've won tons of games like this
in Blitz I've even won an important
rapid game with this trick anat kpof
blundered this in a classical game in
which he played the move A3 against Pia
cromling preparing B4 who can remember
the beautiful trick of Bolt from the
blue if they're ever was one and here
the true reason for placing the queen on
A5 is revealed Knight takes
C4 what the heck is the idea Knight
takes C4 If instead white plays B4 very
importantly you take the Knight and hit
the queen that's a critical detail Queen
E1 look at this queen E1 Queen E1 and
because white played Bishop back to F1
the weakness of F3 is what kills him
Knight F3 check Knight takes Queen and
everything works out perfectly because
the Knight is hanging so when you count
the material you find that white is down
in exchange if white plays Knight G5
then you evacuate your knight with Tempo
Rook C1 Knight takes E3 Knight E6 Knight
F1 Knight G7 Knight D2 and the White
Knight is trapped but even if it wasn't
trapped you could just play Knight takes
G3 and King takes G7 with two extra
pawns so this is just an extra credit
line but still very very cool obviously
okay if white takes the Knight then you
also take the Knight with an extra piece
dude that's the easy
line so that is the gist of this line if
white knows about the trick Knight takes
C4 it's still not that easy to figure
out a way to defend against it because
you can't play Queen D2 that walks right
into the fork does anybody know what
White's best move in this position is
it's a prophylactic move which does I
wouldn't say it kills the line but it
casts a lot of Doubt on this line it is
King G2 the best move and most modern
day GMS know this is to play King G2 and
permanently prevent the possibility of
Knight F3 earlier people would play F4
and chase this Knight out of E5 you can
actually sack the Knight with Knight
takes C4 here and I'm pretty sure that
we did have a speedrun game that went
exactly like this from a practical
standpoint this is a great line for
black white plays F takes E5 if Knight
takes Knight then Queen takes C1 still
works because it hits the bishop but
after fe5 Knight G3 White's position is
exceedingly difficult to play why
because you're about to pick up a third
pawn and if white plays e takes D6
there's yet another beautiful tactic who
can tell me how we continue the
initiative in this position if you're
watching on YouTube make sure to pause
the video This is actually a crucial
resource without this resource the whole
line would fall apart the Kings indion
is often predicated on tactics to make
everything work in the end it's Rook
takes Bishop Rook takes rook and now
it's Bishop D4 right no that blunders
the bishop so how do we pin this Rook we
play Queen C5 and again the queen on A5
makes its presence felt Queen C5 pinning
The Rook well white has to defend the
Rook how does he do it well if he does
it with Queen to D2 and the Knight drops
back to F5 and Black's got way too many
attackers on that Rook white can play
Rook a to E1 but now you simply play
Knight takes E3 if Queen takes E3 then
we win the queen and if Rook takes E3 we
play Bishop H6 hitting where it hurts
white again has to defend the Rook with
the Knight Knight D1 and now we play it
simple we just take the Rook we play
Rook d8 we pick up the pawn and we have
a winning position because we've got the
overwhelming majority on the king side
and White's got the long-term problems
with the King it's about minus two so
instead of Queen to D2 white has to know
the move Queen D3 Which is far from
intuitive and black is still better
Bishop D4 Rook ae1
Knight F5 continuing to apply pressure
with everything that we've got white
continues to defend with everything that
they've got but after Knight takes C3
Knight takes C3 Rook d8 I think that
practically Black's position is better
the engine gives complete equality here
King moves away we play Rook takes D6
and here my file ends with the comment
that black has F fantastic practical
compensation for the sacrificed piece in
the form of two pawns which very likely
will become three pawns because white
has no good way to defend the B uh the
B2 Pawn now if for example white plays
B3 the queen swings over to G5 with the
threat of Queen G3 the threat of Bishop
E5 etc etc and this is after White's
vanish to find all of these moves so I
know these are very technical long lines
I know I'm
probably you know I've lost some people
but for that reason about 10 years ago
this move King G2 was discovered and it
really removed the luster of this line
at like the very top level but at really
any level below 2400 you can play this
safely and the black's position is still
very much playable so even if white
knows the move King G2 I analyze this
with an engine and the best move here is
to actually push H5 and prevent the
further expansion of White's kingside
generally white plays F4 and after
Knight E7 I don't think that white is
much better here honestly I think the
position's close to equal
um because if white plays Bishop D3 then
the Knight reroutes to C5 which is quite
typical in the king's India F4 believe
it or not is an inaccuracy so white
needs to be more patient but it's not
easy for white to find a plan like if
white plays Queen to D2 you drop back on
your own power Knight E7 attacking the
pawn forcing a weakening move such as F3
and now you play against White's dark
squares you play H4 G4 and who can tell
me a very deep positional move that
enables us to prepare to increase our
control over the dark squares on the
king side I'll give you a second it's
Knight H7 it's Knight H7 again exclaim
Knight H7 and the point of this move is
to prepare the move G5 and this is very
similar to what we did in the game once
you play G5 white is stuck saddled with
all these dark Square weaknesses on the
king side and if white ever plays F4 to
try to beat the curve um if white ever
plays F4 to try to beat the curve then
black plays Bishop takes C3 and the E4
Pawn will be lost and with the E4 Pawn
White's whole position starts to crw BC
Knight df6 you're going to take the pawn
with the Knight and black has a big
initiative so from again what I'm trying
to show you not only is how to play this
line from a theoretical standpoint but
also to show you just the the gumption
inherent in this king's Indian line no
matter how white how accurately white
plays there's always going to be
practical problems so that is the
lowdown on the main line unfortunately
in this game white played a very
annoying move there's two annoying lines
that really come close to taking the
queen A5 variation out of commission and
one of them is Bishop E3 the other one
is this move Queen to
C2 um and if I were to make a
recommendation for white it would be
Queen C2 I really think that this move
casts a lot of Doubt on on this
variation because if black plays it the
same way as the The Rook e one line then
white simply plays B3 and none of the
tricks work in this position like
literally none of them so my conclusion
is that Black's best move is to expand
with B5 which leads to a very sharp line
but white is better in the end like B5 I
think the line goes d
d and still like black can absolutely
play this because if white plays cbcb
already I think black is fine I think
think here the position is close to
equal unless white knows a very
difficult move which is to meet black at
the top with B4 white has to know this
move in order to gain an advantage in
this line otherwise black pushes B4 and
puts a lot of pressure on the E4 Pawn by
fening the bishop the point of B4 is to
play Rook B1 black drops around to C4
and white develops a pretty annoying
initiative with a move Bishop A3
basically White's Making a lot of tempo
moves and bringing the other Rook to C1
and black needs to tread very very
carefully here
okay
so finally the move in the game is
another reason why this line is not all
that often played at the top level I
play takes D4 and our opponent responds
with Bishop takes D4 what you need to
know about this line is that I think the
best move is in fact Knight takes D4 and
do not play Knight E5 here because here
after Queen E2 again none of the tricks
really work for black if you try to play
this the same way that you play The Rook
E1 variation white will put the Rook on
D1 this is actually the positional point
of Bishop B3 white is delaying the
development of The Rook so that in the
event of Queen Rook E8 white will be
able to play Rook F D1 and apply
pressure on the D6 Pawn so for instance
if you play Bishop E6 white trades on E6
and The Rook on D1 is placed so much
better than the Rook on E1 here white
has a very instructive and Incredibly
powerful positional move let's see if
anybody can find it I'll be pretty
impressed this is a very hard move white
to play and gain a decisive initiative
and it's not F4 we already know that F4
is almost never all that dangerous I
know most of you are probably thinking
it's F4 and the idea is predicated on
playing F4 but you have to do something
first you strike at the C yeah you
strike at the defile first C5 and only
when black takes and the D file is
opened do you push F4 and E5 driving a
massive wedge into Black's position with
potentially decisive effects in order to
not lose a piece black has to play this
miserable move Knight D5 and just look
at this position like White's White's
winning Rook ad1 is coming Black's
pieces are in sh cbles this is a
disaster so that actually is the point
of Bishop E3 you see how deep it
is for this reason I came to the
conclusion that the only way to keep
this line alive is to play the move
Knight to B6 again just hitting the pawn
same concept just doing it from the from
a safer side and black is worse here
black is worse but you can play this
white has to know Knight B3 hitting the
queen and now you swing the queen over
to the other side the second main idea
of the move Queen A5 is shown in this
line This basically forces an end game
because if white plays G4 then of course
black will play Bishop takes G4 and
develop a massive attack as well as
three pawns for the piece because you're
going to pick up
C4 um so white has to trade queens and
the engine gives about 0. five for white
but I really feel like again Black's
position is very much playable here
white is supposed to go G4
you drop the Knight back to F6 and if
white defends the C4 Pawn then obviously
you bring your Bishop out to E6 and you
could play H5 later you could push D5
I've had this a couple times online and
people really don't show anything here
with white so that is the Lowdown from a
theoretical standpoint now let's get to
the text and let's enter the middle game
our opponent plays Bishop takes D4 okay
so I'm seeing something very interesting
with the end engine which is that
apparently Knight E5 is possible here
it's possible and it's even the top
engine move but I don't like the ensuing
position so apparently after C5 black
can play the very coldblooded Knight F6
back to E8 now obviously it's generally
not a great idea to trade the king's
Indian Bishop but When the Smoke Clears
you get a very playable position for
black slightly worse for sure yeah
slightly worse but very much playable
you're going to bring your Bishop out
you can centralize your queen white
really doesn't have all that much to
write home about but somehow I was under
the impression that C5 almost wins the
game so I decided to delay that move
with Rook to E8 okay Rook to E1 Queen
C7 top engine move here is Knight H2 by
the way crazy how many times has the
move Knight H2 and Knight H7 been a good
move in this game for both sides pretty
ridiculous do you see anybody ever going
Knight H2 I mean that's just crazy do
you know what the idea is I think I
understand the idea the idea is to make
sure that this move does not make
contact with the Knight it's profilaxis
it's prophylaxis you're tucking the
Knight away so that after black plays
Knight E5 you can simply go B3 and this
Knight is not contacting any of White's
pieces right obviously if you do the
same thing here Black's Knight has an
out it can play Knight takes F3 check so
you're moving the Knight away
preemptively okay our opponent plays
Queen C2
we played Knight E5 and Knight D2 I
think is a very strong move I've shown
you guys a lot of examples of mine in
this structure I've shown you probably
three or four games at least where I was
able to win straightforwardly by getting
a knight and putting it on D4 like doing
this Knight D7 f86 D4 one example that I
really really am proud of is a game I
had I think in 2008 let me see if I can
dig it up real quickly this is a that I
had many years ago against Eric
Rodriguez who was a master from
Miami and he Eric Rodriguez was like a
D4 stalwart so it was nice to beat him
at his own
game okay let me just make the board a
little smaller
here all
right so here's how the game went this
was a king's Indian it was a main
line my opponent quickly trades on E5
reaching the same structure that we're
talking about it doesn't matter where
this bishop is it can be on G2 it can be
on E2 it does not change the nature of
the way that this structure works and I
just followed the textbook Knight H5
Knight F4 Knight E6 right you're already
ready to sink the teeth of this Knight
into D4 which is exactly what I did I
played rook d8 and I played Knight C4
and White's position is already
miserable then who can tell me where
should the other I go where does the
Knight on A6 belong in order to butress
the Knight on D4 easy positional
question easy positional question yeah
E6 right you want to go Knight C7 and
Knight E6 simple chess making sure that
this Knight is as stable as it can be
and the rest of the game I developed
some pressure on his B4 Pawn so it's not
enough to put a knight on D4 you also
have to do other stuff in order to
continue keeping your opponent on his
toes A4 Knight D4 now the other Knight
comes in Bishop developed ultimately he
was able to trade the Knight but the
pawn on D4 is a beast and then I was
able to win the game the rest of the
game is outside of the scope of of why
I'm showing you this but ultimately I
had some really nice Maneuvers it wasn't
a perfect game but at the end of the day
the D Pawn was the decisive pawn and
this is the pawn that was spawned no pun
intended by the move Knight D4 so let's
go back to the game continuation
hopefully this makes sense so the
takeaway is that this structure is
almost always very unappetizing for
white with some minor exceptions and
your next move is going to be Knight f8
and Knight E6 hopefully that makes sense
so our opponent made a very mature move
Knight D2 of course if white plays B3
this is what we were talking about
earlier black is able to take on F3 and
take on H3 so this is out of the
question so this only leaves Knight D2
G5 I actually am really proud of this
move I think G5 is a big reason why we
won this game the play that I
demonstrated on the king side and yes
yes I'm sure that black is worse here
maybe even plus over minus but that's
what the Kings Indian is all about and I
think our opponent one of his main
mistakes in this game was maybe to play
a little bit slowly although what he did
initially I think is really really
strong I think the way our opponent set
things up with B3 and Rook D1 is really
well done like he's bringing all of his
P into the center everything is nicely
coordinated and I actually think I
actually am convinced that a big mistake
was to play H takes G4 believe it or not
I actually think this Supernatural move
is a mistake what what do I think white
should have done and why who can tell me
an alternative and I just checked with
the engine white kept a big Advantage
but only by playing this other move H4
why what is the difference between H4
and H takes G4 the difference is very
positional it's subtle now first of all
the H file is Frozen that's a big deal
but that's not the main reason you play
H4 the main reason has to do with
restricting the Knight on F6 this
prevents the Knight H7 Knight G5 idea
that essentially cost white the game
okay so the Knight on F6 dies and this
Pawn chain is able to keep all of
Black's kingside pressure at Bay whereas
in the event of this trade we were able
to get the Knight to G5 and in the end
of the game we were able to use the H
file to develop a decisive attack this
is what these games come down to these
subtle positional moments the computer
evaluation here is plus 1.5 Black's
position is bad and what are some ideas
that white can subsequently have well
this Knight E2 Knight F4 maneuver I
think is particularly strong because the
H5 Pawn is a long-term Target so the
engine gives B5 as a way to try to
generate counterplay which is another
idea that you should always be aware of
as a Kings Indian player B7 B5 the point
is that if white takes the Queens are in
a standoff and White's Queen is
undeveloped is undefended so after B5
white just has to cold blooded
cold-bloodedly respond with Knight E2
and the engine line goes Bishop
A6 now white continues with their plan
Knight F4 BC Knight
C4 now obviously the Knight on E is the
pride and joy of Black's position so you
don't want to give it away you take with
the bishop
BC and Black's position is just a
stinking mess White's got more space
White's got C5 White's got pressure on
H5 I don't see a clear idea for black
yeah you've got a nice Knight on E5
congrats but one nice piece isn't going
to save you so what's interesting is
that if we rewind and we ask her well
where was my mistake yeah probably G5
was a mistake from an objective
standpoint if White had played the
correct move H4 black would have been in
serious trouble positionally um and I I
I admit that and I saw H4 I just figured
we'd figure something out I think this
was the turning point in the game so
instead our opponent plays HG HG and
then Knight E2 and this makes all of the
difference this move Knight H7 it's the
top engine move and this is an equal
position because of this Knight G5 idea
okay so our opponent plays Bishop E3 to
prevent Knight G5 and now we reinforce
the idea with Queen E7 preparing Knight
G5 this was in fact the correct move
well red hot mama was asking if the king
side gets locked with H4 can't you
convert to a queen side attack well
that's exactly what I was trying to do
with the move B5 the problem is that the
C4 Pawn is so well protected white can
just completely ignore like I would not
play CB if I were white and allow black
to generate counterplay down the C file
I would just ignore with Knight
E2 um Luca was proposing Knight fd7
Knight f F to Knight E6 yeah it's
possible but even if the Knight gets to
E6 even if the Knight gets to E6 well
what is it doing there The Bishop's just
going to drop
back so according to the computer let's
see what the computer gives here Knight
E2 knight8 Knight F4 Knight E6 oh wow
look at this line Knight F4 Knight E6
calmly Bishop C3 allowing Knight takes
F4 Knight G6 but white is winning here
Bishop takes G7 King takes G7 F5
apparently is the move now Knight takes
H4 is bad because the Knight will get
stranded and after Knight E5 white
pushes
F4 pushing the other doubled pawn and
essentially Black's King is terrible and
the bishop on C8 is biting on granite so
in the long run Black's King is just not
going to survive the onslaught what
White's going to do here is essentially
move the king over to H1 and use the G
file to blast through even if black puts
a knight on G4 still King H1 Rook G1 and
Bishop H3 totally Unstoppable because
Black's Bishop is never going to be able
to get out of the prison the prison
created by these two pawns engines just
think I mean who would have played like
who would play like this giving up the
E5 square and then pushing the other F
Pawn and it all starts to make sense at
the end so that's the way that you
refute Knight Knight f8 Knight E6 okay
so back we go to the game Queen E7
Knight D4 Queen
F6 Rook F1 I think might be a subsequent
mistake after which black is better and
Bishop H6 top move I think that white
had to go Knight F5 here our opponent
started hesitating because I think he
was sensing that the position was
getting worse but I think white should
play Knight F5 although I don't know
what white should do here feel like
white is out of concrete threats the
engine gives King H2 which is not a
human move oh the idea is Rook H1 and
King G1 okay kind of is Rook h H1 and
King G1 is the
idea so here wow what a line look at
this line black plays Bishop F5 EF and
Bishop H6 now who can tell me why does
this look like a blunder or at at the
very least a very inadvisable
move why does Bishop H6 look like an in
inadvisable move it's because of Knight
E4 but watch these tactics Queen takes
F5 Bishop takes H6 Queen H5 using
the position of White's King to our
advantage then we take the bishop but
white not to be outdone recaptures on
D6 and the position is equal according
to the engine apparently this is an
equal position but I would definitely
take black just because we have such
potential of getting the Knight to G G5
and then F3 White's pieces are kind of
hanging suspended in midair but
objectively the position is about equal
at this point after Rook F1 white is
already worse because we get this move
in and we're able to trade dark squared
Bishops which leaves white with a
terrible Bishop on G2 and this idea of
Knight
G5 is an absolute GameChanger Knight H7
was the game-winning move here so our
opponent kind of resorts to desperation
I think probably C5 was another mistake
but not a big one I think the biggest
mistake our opponent made in this
position was to play Knight F5 I think
after Knight F5 the game is close to
over I think it's close to over what
should white have done well without
thinking white should have played Queen
takes C5 and this is I think a
Grandmaster level observation because
what once black plays Knight D3 99% of
players would reject this line you would
see Knight D3 you see that you lose the
exchange and you think that's losing but
the grandmas would keep calculating
here's what I see after Queen C2 Knight
takes F4 who no Queen C2 Knight F4 e F4
if you look deeply at this position you
start to realize that white has massive
massive compensation for the exchange
first of all White's Pawn structure on
the kingside has been rectified that's a
big plus but white has a specific idea
that allows them to maximize the
activity of the minor pieces while also
restricting Black's Knight what is
likely to be White's next move pause the
video if you're watching on YouTube ask
yourself what White's next move is going
to be so for instance the engine gives
Bishop E6 as the top move it's going to
be E5 to restrict the Knight and open up
a massive Square for the Knight so for
example Rook a d8 you drop the Knight
into E4 that Knight can further go on to
D6 Black's position is already
unpleasant Black's position is already
quite unpleasant here and apparently the
correct line is to play F6 weakening the
bishop white can grab it and play Queen
C4 F5 F5 and you have a Perpetual check
Perpetual check with Queen H six Queen
E3 this is how the game should have
ended so actually after Queen takes C5
the hilarious thing is Knight D3 is
wrong in order to keep an advantage
Black's best bet is to play a simple
move like B6 and chase this queen away
and after Queen C2 for whatever reason
the best move is B5 wow
B5 who can tell me why what is the point
of B5 you play B6 to chase the queen
away that's understandable why is the
best move B5 such an instructive
positional move it's prophylaxis again
prophylaxis
again you stop Knight C4 why is it so
important to stop Knight C4 because that
would trade off Black's strongest piece
the Knight on E5 is what makes Black's
position run okay so if you rush with
Knight G5 white plays Knight C4 and once
this Knight disappears The C6 Pawn
becomes weaker it becomes harder to
attack therefore you cover the two
squares from which White trade that
Knight off C4 and
F3 so profilaxis even in very sharp
positions can be a thing but our
opponent panics he played Knight F5 and
this is the beginning of the end I think
Knight F6 was more accurate but I think
Knight G5 does the job as well and
Knight C4 loses on the spot Knight C4
loses on the spot um to to Knight F3
check apparently the only way to keep
some chances alive was the very
difficult move Knight to E4 but black is
still in fantastic shape we can take on
e4 we can slide the queen over to F6 to
prevent white from playing F6 and
gaining activity then we bring the Rook
into d8 look at that monster Knight look
at White's weaknesses this is minus over
plus so instead Knight C4 Knight E F3
check you might ask why not with the
other Knight because here after King F2
the Knight on E5 is super awkward it's
not doing anything instead if we check
with the other Knight then the knight
from G5 can jump into H3 so look at the
cooperation
between the knights here if White had
played King to F1 then we should not
play Queen H2 because of Queen F2 and
suddenly Black's Queen is stuck in no
man's land instead we should use the
center to our advantage we should play
Rook ad d8 and black is completely
winning notice that white cannot take on
H4 uh G4 because of this Fork if white
plays Bishop F3 you take on F3 you slide
the king over to f8 and much like in the
game all these threats are unstoppable
so this is very simple King F2 and
Knight H3 check removing the final
Defender and once the final Defender is
removed the threats against White's King
have become completely Unstoppable we
zigzag our way to G2 and pick off and
finish off the king with Rook ad to E8
check a final move involves the first
move we make with the Rook which I think
is kind of
artistic what a game so a couple of
concluding thoughts first of all I
introduced you to my favorite line
against the fian ketto and we
kept our analysis to the E4
variation let me be very clear white has
a million Alternatives here you know
there's Bishop G5 there's Queen C2 which
I briefly mentioned there's E3 there's
B3 if you can't play the fian on the
basis of this game alone you can but you
have to study it more diligently but
that would be way way way too much so C6
and queen A5 hopefully I was able to
really bring out the beauty of the
placement of this queen on A5 we focused
on a lot of theory we looked at Rook E1
in depth we looked at Queen C2 there's
other moves there's the move D5 and here
you take take and go B5 expanding on the
queen side won't talk about this one
then we analyzed Knight takes D4 so we
did some Theory and then of course we
talked about the middle game Knight D2
was a very nice move I like this idea of
G5 but the turning point in the whole
game came in this position and I always
say that when we reach a higher level in
the speedrun the games what decides the
games the margins are thinner and
thinner and thinner what decides the
games are much less blunders then you
hit like 16 1700s and it's still big
tactical moments that decide the game or
like massive positional mistakes when
you hit this level it's the subtlest
it's the most nuanced moments that
really decide the game and when I say
decide the game I don't mean lose H
takes G4 is not a losing mistake but it
gives black a very easy game and all of
White's subsequent troubles stem from
the fact that why did not play H4 I
think that's a fascinating aspect of
Chess that things can come down to think
to to such a level of subtlety so
hopefully you enjoyed the game I know
this was very Advanced a lot of theory I
worked really hard to give you as much
as I could um I hope you enjoyed the
game and uh I'm going to end here guys
because this was very very taxing and I
tried super super hard I tried super
hard to uh to play my best I mean we
played a 2400 thank you thank you guys
for hanging out today 5H hour stream lot
of Blitz a lot of bullet a lot of action
a lot of fun thank you everybody
[Music]